<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../interface.xsl"?>
<page>
<filename>TOP/Introduction/History.xml</filename>
<content>
<h1>Quick History</h1>

<p>Table-Oriented Programming was an as then unnamed paradigm that was popular in 
the 80s and 90s.  Common languages that used it were:</p>

<ul>
	<li>dBase</li>
	<li>Clipper</li>
	<li>Harbour/xHarbour (Open Source)</li>
	<li>Visual FoxPro/Microsoft FoxPro</li>
</ul>

<p>These languages had useful features that are not seen in modern programming 
languages.  </p>

<p>With the advent of the internet, and the popularity of Object-Oriented 
Programming, these languages fell out of use.  </p>

<p>In 1998-2002, as the table-oriented languages were falling out of use, 
Tablizer/TOPMind (aka Tablizer/TOPMind) wrote a series of articles 
on "Table-Oriented Programming".  These were, in their own words, unstructured 
and piecemeal.  These advocated for various features prevalent in these 
languages, and a few ideas of their own.  </p>

<p>Unfortunately, at the time, TOP was seen (especially by the biggest TOP 
advocate, Tablizer/TOPMind/TOPMind) as a competitor to OOP.  This meant he spent a lot 
of time criticising the OOP community (often validly) for the weaknesses of OOP 
(and OOP was weak before modern ideas such as the invention of roles).  </p>

<p>This led to a situation where the vast majority of people followed the OOP 
camp, without considering a multi-paradigm approach.  Had more effort been put 
into integrating TOP into modern programming languages, everyone's lives 
would've been a lot easier (or at least most programmers).  </p>

<p>This site is an attempt to make use of the good parts of TOP while hopefully 
leaving behind the oppositional nature of previous discourse on the topic; 
there may still be some pointing out of the weaknesses of various technologies, 
but only with the intent of showing the power of multi-paradigm programming, not 
with the intent of making anyone abandon the named technologies.</p>
</content>
</page>