<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../interface.xsl"?>
<page>
<filename>TOP/Stylistic-Features/Multi-Aspect-Taxonomies.xml</filename>
<content>
<div class="blockquote">

<p>[Even though...] it has been known since 1847 that classifications are 
dependent on the purpose of the classification, people continue to believe that 
it is possible to create a classification system that is context-independent. </p>

<div class="reference">
	Haim Kilov on comp.object, 6/01, quoted in 
	<i><a href="https://www.oocities.org/tablizer/subtypes.htm">Subtype 
		Proliferation Myth</a></i>, by Tablizer/TOPMind
</div>

</div>

<p>(I'm not sure what 6/01 means here; are those numbers days, months, or years?)  </p>

<p>People like to categorise things.  This is good and useful; we human can 
attach the letters or sounds for "ear" to the abstract concept of an ear, and 
then apply it to the individual ears we see.  </p>

<p>However, as stated above, categorising things is only useful to the extent 
that the classification suits the needs of the user.  While some classification 
systems seem obvious to some, that doesn't mean that they are to others.  One 
example I've run across in the past is that a westerner, when asked what a fox 
and a hare have in common, will say things like "four legs, two ears", etc.  But 
people from a more hunting-oriented society will say "fox chases hare" -- their 
abstraction is relevant to the hunting they do to get food.  </p>

<p>Since different people classify things in different ways, it's useful to 
allow for different classification schemes.  Sometimes schemes belong to the 
same axis (ie. the "wool" classification, and the "cloth" classification).  
Other times they are orthogonal (eg. "wool" and "trousers").  When there are 
multiple axes, it's useful to be able to attach each axis to an item.  In 
table-oriented programming, this tends to lean towards one column per axis.  
This means that it's possible to categorise something in multiple ways, and 
filter or sort your data on these axes.  </p>

</content>
</page>
