<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../interface/layout.xsl"?>
<page>
<filename>Language-Support/View.xml</filename>
<sitedir>TOP</sitedir>
<content>
<p>Much like in SQL, views are selections of data from one or more collections 
(descendents of Relation).  However, unlike SQL, we should expect views to be 
local, writable, and objects.  Another notable difference is that it would be 
perfectly normal to declare a view on one table, so as to get a sort order 
or something similar (in SQL terms, they function as a combination of a View 
and a Cursor).  </p>


<h1>Selecting Data</h1>

<h2>Selecting Fields</h2>

<p>This is roughly equivalent to the field list clause in SQL.  </p>

<h3>Field/Property Selection</h3>

<div class="blockquote">

Some operations may only need be done a subset of fields/properties.
For example, one may want to export only a subset of all the fields/properties
available in a collection.

<div class="reference">
	<i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121111043922/http://www.geocities.com/tablizer/collrght.htm">
		Collection Bill of Rights</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

<h3>Field Groups</h3>

<div class="blockquote">

One of the most time-wasting process in programming table processing with 
many of the popular languages is having to type the names of all the fields that 
will show up on a screen or report. It would be much easier to specify the name 
of a set, and all fields belonging to that set would then be used. Although sets 
could be pnumonic names, we chose to use letters in our example for 
simplicity.

<p>Suppose that we had to make a report that showed customer transaction detail, 
but which ommited customer names for reasons of confidentiality. With our setup, 
we could just ask for a report on all fields in set "B" (See the Groups column 
above).  When dealing with tables with 50 plus fields, specifying a set name is 
much simpler than typing 50 names or building a field loop.</p>

<div class="reference">
        <i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121024051826/http://www.geocities.com/tablizer/top.htm">Table-Oriented Programming</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

<h2>Selecting Rows</h2>

<p>This is roughly equivalent to the WHERE in SQL.  </p>

<h3>Filtering</h3>

<div class="blockquote">

<p>This is the ability to view or access a collection through a filter.
Sometimes this is called a "view" (although views can involve
multiple tables or collections, see Joins below.)
It is generally analogous to using a "Where" clause in SQL.
Many of the operations below are to recognize any active
filter(s).</p>

<div class="reference">
	<i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121111043922/http://www.geocities.com/tablizer/collrght.htm">
		Collection Bill of Rights</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

<h3>Searching</h3>
<div class="blockquote">

<p>This is the ability to easily search through a collection to find a specific
row or instance. There are usually indexed searches and un-indexed 
searches. Indexed searches are faster, but require the generation of
an index first (if not already in place). </p>

<p>SQL generally combines searching with filtering using the Where
clause; however, for non-set-oriented processes, this is sometimes
not the most effective way to approach searching.</p>

<div class="reference">
	<i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121111043922/http://www.geocities.com/tablizer/collrght.htm">
		Collection Bill of Rights</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

<h1>Ordering</h1>

<h3>Multiple Virtual Orderings</h3>
<div class="blockquote">

<p>Virtual Ordering is the ordering or
sorting of the collection. "Sorting" usually refers to
a permanent ordering, while "Indexing" refers to a temporary or virtual
sort. Virtual sorts are preferred for large or wide data-sets so that all
actual fields/attributes do not have to be physically moved. (Indexing essentially
uses pointers, but these pointers are not directly visible or accessible
to the programmer.)  </p>

<p>There are usually temporary and permanent
indexes or their equivalent. Temporary indexes are only kept for the duration of 
a loaded application or a predetermined process. Permanent indexes
are kept for the life of a given table or collection that is kept
on disk or long-term storage. (Note that temporary indexes may
still use disk space, but it is assumed that they will be cleaned up
when no longer in use. Thus, they are not limited to RAM size).</p>

<p>Ideally, each element of the collection should be able to be extracted
or read in a specified order. This could be with a filter applied or the
entire collection.</p>

<p>A given collection should be able to have
multiple virtual orderings, although
only one need be active (influencing) at a given time. The ordering
should be maintained even during data changes. Changing the data
should not require an explicit new Order command to restore virtual order
(unless explicitly overridden).</p>

<div class="reference">
	<i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121111043922/http://www.geocities.com/tablizer/collrght.htm">
		Collection Bill of Rights</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

<p>Note that the text below was probably written before eg. Postgres implemented cursors.</p>

<div class="blockquote">

<p>One existing alternative or enhancement
to the SQL set approach can be found in parts of the
<a href="xbasefan.htm">XBase</a> language (and it's dialects).
An XBase-like cursor-oriented approach avoids some of
the problems described above, such as arbitrary
result boundaries, and disjointed adds,
changes, and deletes. (XBase has many problem areas
as a language; thus, I am only talking about
certain features, not necessarily the entire language).</p>
<p>
In Xbase, one traverses tables by selecting (or
making) a single "controlling" index. What appears
in "next" and "previous" record pointer (cursor)
movements depends on the controlling index. 
(Note that an SQL engine has to make a temporary
index anyhow for orders that do not already have
an index for them. However, the fact that SQL does
it automatically is nice.)</p>
<p>
When a new record is added, it defaults to a blank record
(or as described by any defaults). This remains
the current record until the cursor is moved.
Thus, one can add, change, and delete the same record
multiple times without having to reissue queries, unlike SQL.</p>
<p>
Relational operations are done by specifying the
links between two or more tables. When the cursor
for one of the related tables moves, the
cursor for the others is automatically moved.
(An index is needed for the the relation key).</p>
<p>
Note that even though there is only one cursor
at a time, disk buffering in RAM generally
improves the speed of access. Thus, XBase does not
have to necessarily physically read one record
at a time from disk. (This of course depends on the size
and order of physical records).</p>
<p>
XBase is far from perfect, and contains(ed) some
archaic concepts. However, it can serve as a
guide to cursor-oriented approaches and to
integrating collection handling into the language
to reduce DB-engine-to-code-and-back translations.
(The cursor languages built into some of the
commercial RDBMS SQL systems still lack this
integration, beyond API's). </p>
<p>
There are times when the set-oriented approach is
preferred and times when a cursor-oriented approach
is preferred.
Perhaps someday somebody will find
ways to integrate all of them to give us the
<b>best of both worlds</b> in a single package.</p>

<p>
<a name="similar"></a>
I have found that the API's needed for cursor and
set approaches have enough similarities to perhaps
simplify the integration. For one, when traversing
records, set-orientation tends to first collect
a "result set" into an internal buffer, whereas
cursor-orientation tends to fetch each record
as it is requested. (Note that buffering may still
be used to speed up cursoring, however is not tied to
a logical result-set).</p>
<p>
To the application programmer, these approaches look
nearly the same in the code body. Most of the differences
will be in the query or table handle setup code.
Thus, if a collection system offered
both approaches, one could switch from one to the
other without major code changes. Thus, we avoid
any major <a href="meyer1.htm#continuity">continuity</a>
problems.</p>
<pre>
   t = openRecordSetHandle(<b>setUpStuff</b>)
   while getNext(t)
      print t.a
      print t.b
      t.c = foo
      t.b = bar
   end while
   t.save   // may not be needed in some cases
</pre>
<p>Most of the differences would only be in "setUpStuff".
Sometimes cursoring will move the ending condition
into the While loop expression instead of a query.
However, this actually highlights one of the <b>advantages</b> of
cursoring: being able to traverse data without having to
know the end condition (size of result) in advance.</p>

<div class="reference">
	<i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120901201906/http://geocities.com/tablizer/sqlcrit.htm">
		SQL Criticism</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

<h3>Grouping and Totalling</h3>
<div class="blockquote">

<p>This is the ability to obtain summary information based on categories within
the collection or the entire collection. Typical examples include total
sales by region, average sales for the entire collection, etc. SQL usually
performs these using the  "Group By" clause or by aggregate operations
such as Avg(*), Sum(*), Count(*), and so forth. Averages, sums, and counts
can be obtained for sub-categories within the collection or on the entire
collection. </p>
<p>
For category grouping, usually a new collection is generated which contains
the summary information in a similar format to the original. For example,
thousands of sales records my be summarized into five (generated) records
where there is one record for each region (north, south, east, west, and central).</p>


<div class="reference">
	<i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121111043922/http://www.geocities.com/tablizer/collrght.htm">
		Collection Bill of Rights</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

<h1>Joining Collections</h1>

<h3>Joins</h3>
<div class="blockquote">

Some mechanism should be provided for the virtual joining
or relating of two or more collections so that they can be
treated as one collection using the standard operations listed
above. It is sometimes also called "look-up" or "cross-referencing".
Ideally "calculated joins" should be possible so that indexes
or link lists don't have to be manually created in advanced.
(Some operations may not be applicable or practical on virtual joined
collections. This is a controversial topic in the relational
world.)

<div class="reference">
	<i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121111043922/http://www.geocities.com/tablizer/collrght.htm">
		Collection Bill of Rights</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

<p/>

<div class="blockquote">

<p>Ability to temporarily "join" several tables into one virtual table and 
perform operations on it as if it were an actual table. ... This provides 
similar functionality as inherited properties in OOP.</p>

<div class="reference">
        <i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121024051826/http://www.geocities.com/tablizer/top.htm">Table-Oriented Programming</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

<h1>Transferring</h1>

<p>Just a note on Transferring (see <a href="TOP/Collection-Convergence/Relation.xml">
role Relation</a>):</p>

<div class="blockquote">

This is the easy ability to transfer or copy information from one collection to
another. Note that filtering and sorting operations can be used to control the
order and subset of the collection(s) being moved. Either matching field/property
names are used to map one collection into another, and/or an explicit field/property
mapping is provided.

<div class="reference">
	<i><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121111043922/http://www.geocities.com/tablizer/collrght.htm">
		Collection Bill of Rights</a></i>, Tablizer/TOPMind, 1998-2002
</div>
</div>

</content>
</page>
